Greetings
This is a pre-recorded screencast for my
prototype of an "upgrade as a service" done as a
semester project during the fall
to 2011
for
EURECOM in Sophia Antipolis, France
This pre-recorded screencast is
intended to be available in youtube in
order
be prepared for unexpected technical
difficulties
during the project defense
and to provide additional hands on
documentation and record of what I produced
during the semester
so without further introduction
Here we can't see the initial
infrastructure of the set-up
as you can see, i'm running a few elastic
computing instances in Amazon EC2
one of the instances contains the mysql
database and necessary frontend
software we wish to replicate
and upgrade into the new version
and as you can see here we have a up and
running
http-server facing the
public network
and we can work with it
like
any other standard MediaWiki
installation.
And insert data there as you can see.
---
uh... it's a pretty much just a
standard MediaWiki
the other computer here acts as an
external control node
which is used to provide necessary
instructions and setups
for the computing cloud
for the original system under replication
and for the
new dynamically created parallel
universe instance going through the
upgrade
so here we have connected into our
control-computer
giving us our friendly log-in echo as we
open new shells
it does not run in much of a
specialized software except for
configured EC2-tools needed to interact
interact with Amazon Elastic computing
cloud
Over here we can see the GIT
clone from our software repository
it's practically a direct pull from the
latest version
which you can download from the project
GitHub-page
but we have also made our customizations
to the config files
just the state some database
access details
needed for a replication in EC2
we have also run this
a few times so there might be a few
extra dynamically generated files
here and there
which will be
getting overwritten as we go.
And in the program folders we
have the necessary scripts needed to
perform the upgrade
And now I'm going to show you a
sample execution
and try to describe what is happening
behind the screens
so the first software we need to run
is the script creating the replica of the
original amazon instance running mediawiki
1.4
and we can do that by just
executing this
"create_aws_replica.sh" tool
The tool reads the instructions from
config.conf
in order to instruct the Amazon
EC2
to create
the identical copy of the running instance
so as I run the script
it starts to show some amount of
information of the execution
As you see here
the output matches the information on
the Amazon dashboard
we are replicating this instance
ending with "182"
it is notable that in this use
case
that we do not manage to go entirely
without downtime
since the architecture we used to
create a system replica
is the one powering amazon's own image
cloning
we require the system to shut down
the original system for a minute when
cloning the image
and we can see here that amazon
is working with new disk images for
launching the replicated instances
and with a big data set such as
wikipedia, these kind of copying would
of course make a single server system
like the one we are running go down for some
time but for most scalable web
applications they are designed to
withstand a number of shut downs since
severs naturally break down and are
upgraded to handle different loads
vertically and horizontally when you
renew the servers
servers and when you add more
servers
so we assume that in real life
production case we can replace
this kind of replication with traditional node
replication
okay now ask the script has finished
running and
when we look back in the console,
so we can now see that there's a new
instance running
instance is practically a 1:1 copy
or clone of what the original computer
was running
before it got shut down for a few
seconds
and when we get back here are street
happens to be a nice enough to tell us
what they need to do next
so we continue by running this
"setup_replica.sh" which basically copies
the necessary
configuration and software and scripts
the new paralleled universe
so that we can start moving our
operations there
so, let's take the connection into the
newly created node
you can see that the best slightly
different hostnames and
IP's
so it's an independent clone
as I told you before
so here we move into the instructed
directory and follow the next steps
forward
first of all we established a "hookup"
up to the original
user facing mediawiki installation
it's a pretty standard SSH pipe
reading the end of the mysql query log
of the original
and in
essence our computer here will take place is
this replica of the original we also
have an
out to date version off this same log-
file
as is present in the original
node
so in order to receive only subset of
changes
we took the line count from our query log
which represents the state thedatabase
was in just before it got shut down
and replicated
and just take the tail of the file
after that line number
so as I can show you
every query made in to the original
1.4 installation since the shutdown
now
appears in the parallel node
and as we update the mediawiki
like this we can see that the related
logs appearing in the log_cache file
the pipe creates
the second set of instructions contains
all we need to perform the standard
write-locking upgrade from mediawiki
1.4 to 1.5
and actually it downloads the necessary
files from the subversion
repositories of media wiki
and copies the folder to be readable by
our apache server
and after that it runs the necessary
schema-changing database scripts
...and alters the configuration for
mediawiki and apache
so I can show you that in this
different address ah...
uh...
where we enter with our browser we
now have another MediaWiki up and
running
the 1.5 installation has
slightly different symbol over there on
the corner but they still running with much
similar dataset with the old one and their
articles are pretty similar though there are
some updates happening in that
old version because we do not
want to writlock it
and after that
we can start the program doing the sql
translations
these script take the log cache as a
parameter
uh... so when this program runs it
shows it has detected new changes in
the log-file
... right now we can see there is the
same article modification i showed to
demonstrate the ssh-pipe
earlier uh... since we started the
translator the changes start appearing
in the parallel version
and as i insert new data into this
wiki, we can also verify
that these edits also appear to be in
the upgraded version
so in in real life scenario this
recording of queries and appending them
later allows us to have the old version
receiving the user interactions
while the new parallel version works out
the upgrade uninterrupted
after the upgrade has been done we can
"catch up" with the modifications presented
in to the old version
when the two systems are at an equivalent
state
... one just directs the user traffic
of the old node to point into the new node
and then we can stop using excessive
resources in the virtualized cloud
originally allocated to the old version
by just shutting down those
resources
so that's the screencast
for the source code and documentations
look up
to the GitHub address on the description
of this video and i hope uh... these
has been an enlightening experience
for you as much as it was for me
for me.
Thank you.